<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <generator>RSS Builder by B!Soft</generator>
    <title>Matthew Deeprose, accessibility and edtech presentations, blog posts, and projects</title>
    <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io</link>
    <description>Accessibility and edtech presentations, blog posts, and projects by Matthew Deeprose</description>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>Matthew Deeprose</copyright>
    <image>
      <title>Matthew Deeprose, accessibility and edtech presentations, blog posts, and projects</title>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io</link>
      <url>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/image.png</url>
      <width>2000</width>
      <height>1125</height>
    </image>
    <item>
      <title>Accessibility Beyond Borders!</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 09:38:02 +0100</pubDate>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/Accessibility-Beyond-Borders.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[What did we learn from accessibility leaders at six global Higher Education institutions? 
<p>This April, more than 100 people from around the world attended the International Ally User Group's first online panel discussion. </p>
<p>They listened to the experiences of six accessibility experts from six institutions in six different countries. </p>
<p>Up for discussion were five themes relevant to digital accessibility in Higher Education: </p>
<ul>
<li>Raising student awareness of alternative formats. </li>
<li>Engaging staff in accessibility. </li>
<li>Institutional accessibility policies. </li>
<li>Institutional challenges to accessibility. </li>
<li>Accessibility wins.</li></ul>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What one thing can IT staff do to improve accessibility?</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Mar 2023 07:53:45 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://generic.wordpress.soton.ac.uk/digital-learning/2023/03/22/what-one-thing-can-it-staff-do-to-improve-accessibility/</link>
      <description><![CDATA[What’s one activity that everyone who works in an information technology related field could do to make a difference to digital accessibility? The answer could be right in front of you as you read this: your keyboard.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How can we correct captions and create transcripts at the University of Southampton?</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 08:41:03 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://generic.wordpress.soton.ac.uk/digital-learning/2023/03/17/how-can-we-correct-captions-and-create-transcripts-at-the-university-of-southampton/</link>
      <description><![CDATA[Captions on videos benefit everyone. It’s important that captions are accurate and follow good practice. Learn how to improve captions using University tools.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How did we make the University’s Teaching Excellence Framework (TEF) submission more accessible?</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 1 Mar 2023 06:44:11 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://generic.wordpress.soton.ac.uk/digital-learning/2023/02/24/tef-accessibility/</link>
      <category>accessibility</category>
      <description><![CDATA[A case study with examples of improving document accessibility. This is based around the work I did on improving the accessibility of the University of Southampton's Teaching Excellence Framework submission.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making accessibility easier</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 15:29:26 +0100</pubDate>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/making_accessibility_easier.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[My presentation to the European Ally User Group, sharing: what I learned while designing a session about writing alternative text for complex images like graphs and charts, an approach to making on-brand colour contrast easier, turning the Microsoft Accessibility inspector on by default. Implementation plan, and the start of communicating the change.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Better content, made easy: using the accessibility inspector in Word, PowerPoint, and Excel</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 06:32:50 +0100</pubDate>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/better_content_made_easy.html</link>
      <category>accessibility</category>
      <description><![CDATA[In this session we introduce the accessibility inspector in Word, PowerPoint, and Excel. The accessibility inspector: 
<ul>
<li>identifies possible improvements you can make to the accessibility of your documents </li>
<li>runs whilst you’re working </li>
<li>will show you how to make your document more accessible. </li></ul>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Use group policy to set the Microsoft Office Accessibility Inspector to "check while you work" by default</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 15:31:40 +0100</pubDate>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/inspector_for_all</link>
      <category>accessibility, group policy</category>
      <description><![CDATA[The Accessibility Inspector in Office is a useful tool that helps content creators identify accessibility potential improvements while they create content in Word, PowerPoint, and Excel. The tool does not run by default. A user has to follow three steps to turn it on.

To promote the use of this tool we arranged to have the accessibility inspector run by default on University-managed desktops and laptops running Windows with Microsoft 365.

We have now successfully implemented this change. It's early days but feedback so far is positive. Here is a slightly anonymised implementation plan, with thanks to my colleague Nick Williams for sharing it.

This guidance is provided on a best-efforts basis. It should be tested in a pre-production environment first. No guarantees or assurances etc.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UoS Brand Accessible Colour Suggester</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 6 Sep 2022 09:55:09 +0100</pubDate>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/infographic-colour-generator.html</link>
      <category>accessibility, colour contrast</category>
      <description><![CDATA[I created this simple tool that ranomly chooses a set of colours from our corporate brand that all meet accessibility guidelines for contrast. This was an interesting learning experience to help me learn a bit more about Javascript and ARIA. I hope to spend some more time improving this for a future more extendable iteration.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two steps forward? Making accessibility easier.</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 4 Aug 2022 07:43:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/two-steps</link>
      <category>accessibility</category>
      <description><![CDATA[The UCISA-UX team asked whether we "made something easier for everyone to use"? In this five-minute slot I will share two topics on that theme:

Brand colour contrast made easy
Accessibility inspector for everyone]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Download Blackboard Collaborate Videos, even when downloading not enabled.</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2022 15:31:33 +0100</pubDate>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/collab-dl.html</link>
      <category>Blackboard</category>
      <description><![CDATA[Course instructors may forget to allow recordings of their Blackboard sessions. In this post I share a workaround to get you the mp4 of the recording for offline usage.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is alternative text? How do I write it for images, charts, and graphs?</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 17:00:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/alt-text-images-charts-graphs.html</link>
      <category>Accessibility</category>
      <description><![CDATA[What do we mean by alternative text? Who is it useful for? What strategies can we use for writing it? How might we write alternative text for more complex images like graphs, flow charts, and venn diagrams? I attempt to explain in this video. It was recorded live as a webinar for the University of Southampton's Office 365 Community. I've included the questions and answers from the session.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sustaining accessibility efforts through accessibility-related appraisal objectives</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2022 07:12:45 +0100</pubDate>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/objectives.html</link>
      <category>accessibility</category>
      <description><![CDATA[How can IT departments sustain their accessibility efforts? While there are vital procedural and technical answers we should also consider the importance of cultural change. In this presentation, Tamsyn Smith and Matthew Deeprose will discuss early work on embedding accessibility within appraisal objectives.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PowerBI: Accessibility Tips</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 3 Apr 2022 16:28:35 +0100</pubDate>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/powerBI.html</link>
      <category>accessibility</category>
      <description><![CDATA[What can we do to make our PowerBI reports more accessible? In this 20 minute presentation I explain the four principles of the Web Content Accessibility Guidelines and how they relate to the creation of PowerBI reports.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The impact that high quality mark-up can have on accessibility, performance, and discoverability</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2022 16:55:27 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/high_quality-markup_impact.html</link>
      <category>accessibility</category>
      <description><![CDATA[Going beyond accessibility checklists, you may quickly get bogged down with technical details and acronyms that you feel you may never understand. In this fast-paced 30-minute presentation I use worked examples, with screen reader demonstrations, to cover topics including:

-semantic landmarks
--using ARIA attributes to improve the screen reader experience
-respecting motion and colour preference
-dark and light themes
-the new contrast measurement in WCAG 3
-and more

My hope is that by the end of this presentation you feel more informed and ready to dive deeper into web accessibility.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interview with textBOX</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jan 2022 14:13:18 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.textboxdigital.com/lunchbox-011</link>
      <category>Accessibility</category>
      <description><![CDATA[TextBox are well know for their accessibility work, most recently the ASPIRE awards. Huw Alexander from TextBox invited me to do an interview for their Lunchbox series.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accessibility Newsletters and Blogs</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jan 2022 15:42:57 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/resources.html</link>
      <category>Accessibility</category>
      <description><![CDATA[I've compiled a list of accessibility newsletters and blogs. ]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>iSolutions Digital Accessibility Community of Practice: what did we do in 2021 and what was the impact?</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 08:29:38 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://generic.wordpress.soton.ac.uk/digital-learning/2022/01/17/da_cop_2021_review/</link>
      <category>Blog post</category>
      <description><![CDATA[]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making IT accessible for all!</title>
      <pubDate>Fri, 3 Dec 2021 08:28:46 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/makeITaccessible.html</link>
      <category>Presentation</category>
      <description><![CDATA[Recent experiences have demonstrated that University staff and students expect to use online resources with a variety of devices, making full use of accessibility features such as reflow, captions, and text-to-speech.

Such features benefit everyone, but especially the increasing proportion of university students who self-report a disability.

University Information Technology departments know they must commit to accessibility; indeed, they have a legal obligation to do so, but how can they take this ambition and embed accessibility within their policies and processes?

In this presentation, we will share:

approaches to building a digital accessibility policy for university IT departments.
techniques for embedding accessibility within IT development processes by ‘shifting left’.
examples from within the Higher Education and wider IT sectors.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accessibility Allies Resources</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 3 Nov 2021 08:27:28 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://generic.wordpress.soton.ac.uk/digital-learning/accessibility-allies/</link>
      <category>Resources</category>
      <description><![CDATA[We share these materials as part of our presentation Accessibility Allies at the University of Southampton. The content may contain errors or omissions. We share this on a best-efforts basis.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Worldwide Digital Accessibility - 001 - Just sit down and do it!</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 3 Nov 2021 08:26:06 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/WDA001.html</link>
      <category>Interview</category>
      <description><![CDATA[Not a presentation as such, but the magnificent Cam Beaudoin invited Peter J. Jonas and I to take part in the first Worldwide Digital Accessibility vodcast.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accessibility Allies at the University of Southampton</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 2 Nov 2021 08:24:56 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/allies.html</link>
      <category>Presentation</category>
      <description><![CDATA[The University of Southampton introduced Blackboard Ally (a tool that provides insight into an institution's accessibility) in Summer 2021. To support the rollout, five student interns were employed over the summer as “Accessibility Allies”.

In this webinar, the University's Digital Learning Team shared how they organised the project and provided information about the work undertaken by the students and outlined how they achieved impressive results.

Students were involved with remediating course content to make it more digitally accessible, and advised academic staff about how to improve accessibility, among other things. Their work resulted in an average 87% increase in course file accessibility score, benefiting more than 6,000 students.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accessibility does not impede agility! Six ways that Digital Accessibility maps to Agile Practices</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 08:21:46 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://generic.wordpress.soton.ac.uk/digital-learning/author/matthew-deeprose/</link>
      <category>Blog post</category>
      <description><![CDATA[A common misconception is that Digital Accessibility slows down and impedes IT development process, making them less agile. In this post we cover six aspects we learned in our Agile training course and how they relate to accessibility.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three ways PowerPoint’s "Design Ideas" excludes your audience, and how to fix it.</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jul 2021 08:10:52 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://generic.wordpress.soton.ac.uk/digital-learning/2021/07/20/design-ideas-three-ways-overview/</link>
      <category>Blog post</category>
      <description><![CDATA[PowerPoint’s Design Ideas feature helps us create attractive slides quickly. Unfortunately, some of its suggestions do not follow accessibility best practice, creating barriers that may exclude members of your audience. In this blog post we explain three issues and how to fix them.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward amazing accessibility!</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 08:07:44 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://matthewdeeprose.github.io/amazing.html</link>
      <category>Presentation</category>
      <description><![CDATA[IT departments in the Higher Education sector and elsewhere know they must commit to accessibility, but how can we take this ambition and embed it within our operations?

Within the University of Southampton IT department (which is named iSolutions) senior leadership committed to delivering "amazing accessibility" but has not yet set out how this might happen.

In this internal presentation within the department, held on Global Accessibility Awareness Day on 20 May 2021, I attempt to show how we could start that journey.]]></description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>